Soviet Union Methodist Church Subject Files, Inclusive: 1962-2000, undated, Bulk: 1977-1985.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Methodist Church Subject Files
Inclusive: 1962-2000, undated, Bulk: 1977-1985.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
50
Keston Institute, 1969 -
23 folders
The Soviet Union Methodist Files contain a variety of materials on the churches, congregations, and leaders of the Methodist church in Estonia, the Soviet Union, and Ukraine.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
The Keston Center received materials regarding the Soviet Union Methodists from 1962 through 2000. The majority of the content regards the Methodist church in Estonia, Ukraine, and the regions of Moscow and St. Petersburg, and specifically focuses on these churches’ size, services, membership, and leaders.
Methodism spread to Russia in the late 1800s through the influence of Finnish missionaries. In 1910, Methodism was formalized in Estonia. Methodist churches were closed in the 1920s and 1930s. For at least the next sixty years, the majority of Methodist congregations in the Soviet Union region were located in Estonia, although there were two singular congregations in Ukraine and Russia.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Methodist Files contain articles, letters, correspondence, clippings, newspaper, bibliographies, press releases, booklets, book chapters, abstracts, photographs, and manuscripts. These documents span from 1962-2000 with primary focus on 1977-1985.
The majority of the content details the size, membership, leaders, and services of the Methodist church in the Soviet Union, Estonia, and Ukraine. Special focus is given to these churches regionally and individually. Specific places and people mentioned include Olav Parnamets, Alexander Kuum, Estonia, Herbert Murd, Ole Borgen, and Harold Altok.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Methodist documents organized by topic. The original filing system has been preserved with documents in each folder organized by date. In a few cases, folders were added to accommodate documents with subject designations that had no folder. The Keston Center received the Estonian-specific Methodist items in a few separate files. These have been further organized by date.
The Soviet Union Methodists Subject Files have been organized into three series: I. Estonia, II. General, and III. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 50.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Subjects
Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Methodist Church -- Estonia.; Methodist Church -- Soviet Union -- History.; Methodist church buildings
Genres
Abstracts.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Booklets.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Newspapers.; Photographs.; Press releases.
- Estonian Methodist Church, 1966-1999; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series focuses specifically on the Methodist church in Estonia and discusses leaders, movements, and persecution.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 50.
  - Estonian Methodist Church. General (1 of 2), 1966 October, 1971 July-August, 1973-1976, 1979 May-October, 1980 March-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Estonian Methodist Church. General (2 of 2), 1981 September, 1983 February, 1987 February-November, 1988 February-May, 1966 November, 1999 August-October, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Estonian Methodist Church. Letters and Photos, 1980-1982, 1986 April, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General, 1962-2000; 2
  This series reviews the Methodist church in Estonia, Ukraine, and the Soviet Union. It discusses leaders, individual churches, church numbers, church sizes, and movements within the Methodist church as a whole. It also briefly mentions accounts of persecution, primarily the case of Herbert Murd.
  - Methodist Church. General, 1991 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Methodist Church. References, 1962-1973, 1978 December, 1982 October, 1987 April, 2000 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Methodist Church. History, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Methodist Church Administration. Individual Churches, 1974 August, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Methodist Church-State Relations, 1980 March-April (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church, 1981 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church. Interrogations, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church. Imprisonment (arrests, labour camp, prison), 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church. Discrimination in employment, 1981 November (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church. Attacks in the media, at public meetings, etc., 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Methodist Church. House searches; confiscation of literature, property, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Methodist Church Life, 1985 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Methodist Church Life. Festivals and anniversaries, 1982 November (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Methodist Church Life. Preaching; evangelism; conversions, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Methodist Church Life. Revival; Charismatic Renewal, 1989 April, 2001 April (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Individual Methodist Clergy, 1966 December, 1979 April-June, 1983 August-October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Methodist Church. International Relations: Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1985 January-March (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Methodist Church. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State: Contacts with Foreigners, Emigres, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Methodist Church. Relations with Fellow Believers (Great Britain and U.S.), 1985 May-August, 1999 February-March (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Samizdat, 1983; 3
  This series includes samizdat discussing discrimination in employment.
  - Methodist Church. Discrimination in Employment, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)